Hi, I'm Nur Hamim. I'm currently passionate about Open Source, Linux, and Cloud Computing.
大家好，我是Nur Hamim。我喜歡研究Linux、開源和雲端計算。
Currently I am also active in several Linux communities in Indonesia and I am the founder of BelajarLinux.id,
我活躍於許多印尼的 Linux 社群，我是 BelajarLinux.id 的創始人，
and I work at PT. Biznet GIO Nusantara as Product Operation Engineer.
我在 PT. Biznet GIO Nusantara 擔任產品運營工程師。
At the Ubuntu Conference Asia 2021 this time I will bring the theme Private Lab Virtualization
這次在 Ubuntu Conference Asia 2021 ，我將介紹使用multipass進行虛擬化
using multipass and deploy web-based apps on the Ubuntu Server Virtual Machine that is on multipass.
和在multipass的 Ubuntu 伺服器虛擬機上部署網路應用程式。
Let's get acquainted with multipass. What is multipass?
先讓我們了解一下什麼是multipass？
Multipass is a virtualization and one of the products from Canonical, Ubuntu. Multipass is used to create a Virtual Machine. Multipass support with cloud-init, just like the public cloud.
Multipass 是一種虛擬化，是 Canonical的產品之一。Multipass 用於創建虛擬機。multipass支援cloud-init，就像公有雲一樣。
Multipass can run in the local environment, or on the computer or on our respective laptops.
Multipass 可以在本地環境中運行，也可以在電腦或我們的筆記型電腦上運行。
Multipass itself is free and highly recommended for development.
Multipass 本身是免費的，強烈推薦用於開發。
Why should we use multipass? Multipass is very light and very simple and easy to use.
為什麼要使用Multipass？Multipass 非常輕便，非常簡單易用。
When we are creating a VM and we want to delete a VM in multipass it is very easy.
當我們創建一個虛擬機並且想要在multipass中刪除一個虛擬機時，這很容易。
Multipass also works as a virtual machine manager.
Multipass 還可用作虛擬機管理器。
Multipass can be installed on several operating systems such as Linux, Windows, and Mac OS.
Multipass 可以安裝在多個作業系統上，例如 Linux、Windows 和 Mac OS。
Multipass is designed for developers who want to use Ubuntu-based virtual machines.
Multipass 是為想要使用基於 Ubuntu 虛擬機的開發者設計的。
Next we will explain the difference between multipass and VirtualBox.
接下來我們將解釋 multipass 和 VirtualBox 之間的區別。
We all know about VirtualBox, which is a virtual manager that can create a virtual machine.
我們都知道VirtualBox，它是一個可以創建虛擬機的虛擬管理器。
In virtualbox we have provided a variety of OS choices templates. Starting from Windows,
在 virtualbox 中，我們提供了多種作業系統選擇模板。像是 Windows ，
Linux, and so on. But if we want to create a virtual machine inside
Linux等等。但是如果我們想在VirtualBox創建一個虛擬機
VirtualBox, we must have an ISO that we can use to create a virtual machine.
我們必須有一個可以用來創建虛擬機的 ISO。
In contrast to multipass. Multipass is very flexible. The first,
相較之下，Multipass 會比較彈性些。首先，
multipass has provided several Ubuntu operating system templates starting from Ubuntu 18,04,
multipass 提供了幾個 Ubuntu 作業系統模板，從 Ubuntu 18,04 開始，
20.04, 21.04. And we can also create an operating system or virtual machine in multipass
20.04、21.04。我們也可以在multipass中創建作業系統或
with several other operating systems. And the process of creating virtual machines in multipass
其他作業系統的虛擬機。在multipass中創建虛擬機的過程
just only run one command. Not like VirtualBox, which uses
只需要執行一個命令。不像 VirtualBox，
a few steps. Starting from uploading ISO, creating new virtual machine, starting virtual machine. And
從上傳 ISO 開始，創建新的虛擬機，啟動虛擬機，需要多個步驟。
it really takes time. Next I will explain the differences between multipass and
這真的花時間。接下來我將解釋 multipass 和 Docker 之間的區別
docker. We already know docker is virtualization at the application level. If we have a
我們已經知道 docker 是應用程式級別的虛擬化。如果我們有一個
containerized applications, these applications can be easily run inside the
容器化的應用程式，這些應用程式可以很容易地在Docker執行
docker. The difference is very basic between multipass and docker. Multipass itself is one
multipass 和 docker 之間的區別是非常基本的。Multipass 本身就是一個
of the virtualization in the operating system. Docker can run over multipass. Therefore,
作業系統中的虛擬化。Docker 可以在multipass運作。所以，
Developers in development are very well suited to using multipass. Because in multipass
對於開發中的開發人員，非常適合使用multipass。因為在multipass
we are very efficient and flexible. We can run an app directly or a service.
非常高效和靈活。我們可以直接運行應用程式或服務。
for example docker. Next I will explain the difference between multipass, VirtualBox, and LXD.
像是Docker。接下來我會解釋 multipass、VirtualBox 和 LXD 之間的區別。
Multipass is one of the experiences from Ubuntu that is specialized for development that can
Multipass 是 Ubuntu 的實踐之一，專門用於開發，可以
running on multiple operating system platforms. For example multipass can run on Linux, Windows,
在多個作業系統上運行。例如 multipass 可以在 Linux、Windows、
and Mac OS. So anyone or developer can use multipass on the operating system.
和 Mac OS執行。因此任何人或開發人員都可以在作業系統上使用Multipass。
And a developer doesn't need a special virtualization to run multipass
而且開發人員不需要特殊的虛擬化來執行Multipass
if on Windows we can use Hyper-V or VirtualBox. While on Mac OS we can
如果在 Windows 上，我們可以使用 Hyper-V 或 VirtualBox。在 Mac OS 上，我們可以
using hyperkit or VirtualBox and on Linux we can use LXD. Here are
使用 hyperkit 或 VirtualBox，在 Linux 上我們可以使用 LXD。這裡有
flows from multipass. The bottom is the host. This host can use Linux or Mac OS or
從Multipass的流程。底部是主機。此主機可以是 Linux、Mac OS 或
windows. So adjust to the environment that we have. Next there is the userspace multipass.
Windows。所以可以使用我們現有的環境。接下來是userspace Multipass。
This is where the system or service is installed on the host. Above userspace multipass then
這是系統或服務安裝在主機上的位置。在userspace Multipass上面
we can create various kinds of virtual machines. The virtual machine can use Ubuntu,
可以創建各種虛擬機。虛擬機可以使用Ubuntu，
can use CentOS, can use Rocky Linux and so on.
可以用CentOS，可以用Rocky Linux等等。
Inside the virtual machine, we can install or deploy a service just like the docker service or we
在虛擬機內部，我們可以安裝或部署像docker的服務，或者我們
can directly deploy an app in the virtual machine. Next I will explain
可以直接在虛擬機中部署一個應用程式。接下來我會解釋
the advantages and disadvantages of the first multipass in terms of the advantages of multipass it is very easy
multipass的優缺點，就優點來說，Multipass十分簡易
and simple. And very fast in creating a virtual machine. Why? Because multipass
而且創建虛擬機的速度非常快。為什麼？因為Multipass
already provided a template or default Ubuntu images. If we want to make a
已經提供了模板或預設的 Ubuntu 映像。如果我們想做一個
Ubuntu virtual machine, we can run only one command line and quickly multipass
ubuntu虛擬機，我們可以只執行一個命令行，接著multipass便會快速地
will create a virtual machine. If we want to create a virtual machine other than the Ubuntu OS,
創建一個虛擬機。如果我們要創建 Ubuntu 作業系統以外的虛擬機，
we can do that too. By downloading an image cloud that is already available
我們也可以透過在每個作業系統的存儲庫中
in each operating system's repository. For example CentOS, we can download first
下載已經可用的磁碟映像(image cloud)。以CentOS為例，我們可以先下載
first CentOS cloud image first. Then we can run the command line to create a
CentOS 的磁碟映像(image cloud)。然後我們可以執行命令來創建一個
virtual machine with the virtual pass using the CentOS image. Next multipass
使用 CentOS 映像的具有virtual pass的虛擬機。下一個multipass的優點是，
one of the most modern management virtual machines and very suitable for a developer
它是最現代的管理虛擬機之一，非常適合正在進行開發的
whose needs are for development. Because it is very simple and easy to use. Multipass
開發人員，因為它非常簡單易用。十分推薦
indeed recommended for development. So if we want to make a production level
使用Multipass進行開發。所以如果我們想製作一個生產級別
development, we can use a virtual pass to run an app or the operating system.
開發，我們可以使用virtual pass來執行應用程式或作業系統。
Then what are the disadvantages of multipass? When we have created a virtual machine then
那麼multipass的缺點是什麼呢？當我們創建了一個虛擬機之後
we cannot resize the specifications that we have previously set automatically.
我們無法調整之前自動設置的規格。
How to resize a virtual machine that we have created?
那麼如何調整我們創建的虛擬機的大小？
The solution is to stop the virtual machine first. Then we adjust it manually. The second is,
解決辦法是先停止虛擬機。然後我們手動調整。第二個缺點是，
The default multipass in the Virtual machine is only one interface available.
虛擬機中預設的Multipass只有一個可用介面。
The third multipass by default only provides a few images. One of them is just an Ubuntu image
第三個缺點是，預設情況下Multipass僅提供少數映像。 Ubuntu 映像
and image apps that have been bundled. Examples such as image k3s or image nextcloud. Use case
和已綁定的映像應用程式是其中之一。 k3s 映像或 nextcloud映像。
which is often used by development in multipass, namely using a kubernetes cluster in multipass.
在Multipass開發中經常使用它，也就是在Multipass中使用 kubernetes 叢集。
Multipass is an alternative to docker. Separate Kubernetes cluster running on top
Multipass 是 相對於docker 的另一選擇。通常被使用的是docker或容器。
containers. Usually what is often used is docker or containerd. With multipass
有了Multipass，
we can run a docker over multipass and we can run a Kubernetes Cluster on
我們可以在 multipass 上運行一個 docker，然後我們可以在Docker上面運行一個 Kubernetes 叢集
the docker. Or we can also directly run a kubernetes cluster in
或者我們也可以直接在虛擬機或Multipass上的虛擬機
VMs or virtual machines in multipass. Why? because multipass already supports metadata
執行一個kubernetes叢集。為什麼？因為 multipass 已經支持metadata cloud-init
cloud-init. In cloud-init we can customize any service or package needed by the user
在 cloud-init 中，我們可以自訂使用者需要的任何服務或
the kubernets cluster. Here are some references that can be used for deployments
Kubernetes 叢集。以下是一些kubernetes叢集部署的參考資料
on kubernetes cluster. Next we will explain the basics of cloud-init.
接下來我們將解釋cloud-init的基本概念。
Cloud-init is a standard for customizing an instance cloud like a public cloud. Very
Cloud-init 是用於自定義實例雲(instance cloud)（如公有雲）的標準。
many public clouds use template cloud-init images. For example openstack.
許多公有雲使用 cloud-init 映像模板。例如openstack。
OpenStack can use cloud-init too. In multipass we can also use cloud-init.
OpenStack 也可以使用 cloud-init。在Multipass，我們也可以使用 cloud-init。
Therefore, it is highly recommended for developers to use multipass as a tool
因此，強烈推薦開發者使用 multipass
virtualization media lab suited to development. An example of a cloud-init configuration,
這裡是一個 cloud-init 設定的例子，
here is SSH. How is SSH used to login to virtual machines using key
這是SSH。SSH使用密鑰登錄虛擬機
later on. And here we can also determine does the package update the operating system directly?
在這裡我們也可以確定封包(package)是否直接更新作業系統
updated or upgraded? Here is an example [True]. It means later on in the process of creating
更新或升級？在這裡是True。這表示之後在創建虛擬機
virtual machine, the package is already automatically updated. And here is the packages menu. Packages
過程中，package已經自動更新了。這是package menu。
we can determine this. We want to use what package in the operating system we make or
我們可以決定要使用我們製作的作業系統或我們創建的虛擬機中
in the Virtual machine we create. Here we will use packages git, vim, wget, even we
的什麼package。這裡我們使用 git、vim、wget，我們甚至
can use docker package directly and here is the runcmd command line. Ah, here it is
可以直接使用 docker package，這裡是 runcmd 命令行。啊，就是這個
which will automatically execute the package. Then the package is a function for lists
這會自動執行package。這個package會列出需要
what packages to install. If the runcmd function is to run or
安裝什麼package。是否 runcmd 函數將要執行或
running an installed package. Then How to install multipass? Such that
正在已安裝的package上運行。那麼如何安裝multipass？
we know multipass can run on various operating system. Starting from Linux, Windows,
我們知道 multipass 可以在許多作業系統上運行。從 Linux、Windows ，
and Mac OS. Let's see how easy it is. We install a multipass in the operating system
到 Mac OS。讓我們看看它有多容易。我們在Linux上安裝了一個Multipass
Linux. On the Linux operating system, to run multipass we can run with one
在 Linux 作業系統上，要運行 multipass ，我們可以只執行一行
command line only. Already available on snapd using the command "snap install multipass".
命令。可以使用snap，使用命令“snap install multipass”。
If we use architecture other than amd64 then we can also run a multipass.
如果我們使用 amd64 以外的架構，我們也可以執行Multipass。
Therefore, multipass does not require special virtualization. So all virtualization
因此，Multipass不需要特殊的虛擬化。所有的虛擬化
it can run a multipass. Then how do we use Windows? and we want
都可以執行Multipass。那麼我們如何在Windows使用呢？
running a multipass. Multipass already provides a package for Windows that can
Multipass 已經為 Windows 提供了一個包，
we download and we install like installing an application on Windows. However, it should be noted in
我們可以下載並安裝，就像在 Windows 上安裝應用程式一樣。但是，需要注意的是
Windows has some Windows requirements that can support multipass. Including Windows 10
Windows 有一些支援Multipass的版本要求。包含 Windows 10 Pro、
Pro, Enterprise, and Education. Or we can combine Windows with
企業版和教育版。或者我們可以將 Windows 與
VirtualBox to run a multipass. Then if on Mac OS it is the same as in
VirtualBox 結合來運行Multipass。如果是在 Mac OS 上，
Windows. Multipass already provides a package that can be installed on Mac OS. To install a
和在Windows上一樣。Multipass 已經提供了一個可以安裝在 Mac OS 上的包。安裝multipass
multipass on Mac OS it is the same as we install an application on Mac OS. and if we want
在Mac OS 和我們在 Mac OS 上安裝應用程式相同。如果我們想要
using multipass as well as VirtualBox together and its VirtualBox as
一起使用 multipass 和 VirtualBox 而且用 VirtualBox 作為
Manager of VM multipass, we can set a driver by default
multipass虛擬機的管理器，我們可以設定一個驅動程式
it becomes VirtualBox. But if we don't need not use VirtualBox on Mac OS,
預設為 VirtualBox。但是如果我們不需要在 Mac OS 上使用 VirtualBox，
we do not need to set the driver. Because automatically every time we install a
我們就不需要設定驅動程式。因為每次我們安裝一個
multipass, the multipass driver will be installed automatically. And we can use it directly. Here are some Command Lines from multipass. There are so many basic command-line that
multipass，將自動安裝 multipass 驅動程式。然後就可以直接使用它。這裡有一些 multipass 的命令行。有很多
we can use in multipass. from "multipass -h" to see display help
我們可以在Multipass使用的基本命令。從“multipass -h”查看顯示幫助
like this or help. Then there are some command line that we can use. Starting from delete,
像這樣或--help。然後有一些我們可以使用的命令。從刪除開始，
Its function is to delete an instance, "exec" to run or execute
它的作用是刪除一個實例 (instance)，“exec” 用來運行或執行
instances. Indirectly or without us login to the instance we can use
實例。在間接或不需要登入到實例的情況下
The exec. There is also "find" to search for a image that is in multipass. "get" the function for
可以使用 "exec" 。還有 “find” 來搜索multipass映像。“get”用來
fetches an existing configuration in instances. There is also "help" for assistance. "info" for
獲取實例中的現有配置。也有“help”指令來協助你。“info”用來
view detailed information of existing instances we make. There is also "recover", there is also "purge", and
查看我們製作的現有實例的詳細資料。也有“recover”，也有“plurge”，還有
"restart" and other basic commands. I will show these basic commands
“restart”和其他基本命令。我會在下一投影片
on the next slide. Ah, on this slide I will explain how to use
展示這些基本命令。在這張投影片我會解釋如何使用
multipass. As we already know previously multipass has so many command-line
Multipass。正如我們之前已經知道的， multipass 有如此多
that can be run easily. The first one starts from "find". "multipass find". It means we are looking for an image
容易執行的命令行。第一個從 “find” 開始。“multipass find”。這表示我們正在尋找
which is in the multipass. Then, how if we want to create a virtual machine
在Multipass裡的映象。那麼，如果我們要在Multipass
in multipass? We can use option launch "multipass launch". at this "launch" we
創建一個虛擬機呢？我們可以使用launch，“multipass launch”。在 “launch” ，
can specify a parameter. Starting from the CPU, memory, disk, even we can specify network--
我們可以指定一個參數。從CPU、記憶體、磁碟，甚至我們可以指定網絡——
What network will we use in multipass. For example, here I provide four
我們將在Multipass中使用什麼網絡。舉例來說，這裡我提供四個
example. The first example is multipass launch 20.04. That means we will create a virtual
例子。第一個例子是 "multipass launch 20.04"。這意味著我們將創建一個
machine with Ubuntu 20.04 operating system with the name virtual machine instance-demo --cpu.
裝有 Ubuntu 20.04 作業系，名稱為 instance-demo 的虛擬機。
That means we declare the CPU that will be used by a 2GB multipass. --memory,
"--cpu" 表示著我們聲明了 2GB Multipass將使用 CPU。 “--memory”，
Here the memory will be used which is 2GB and disk that is 5GB. Ah, here we are actually
這裡使用 2GB 的記憶體和 5GB 的磁碟。啊，實際上，我們在這裡
can customize the specifications of the instance or VM that we need. Example
可以自定義我們需要的實例或虛擬機的規格。
the second we create an instance however by using cloud-init. Or the image that
第二個例子我們使用 cloud-init 或者已經自定義的映像創建一個實例。
we have customized. The third example is create a virtual machine with an image
第三個例子是創建一個Ubuntu映像的虛擬機
other than on Ubuntu. As we know that multipass only provided Ubuntu
我們知道，multipass 只提供了 Ubuntu 映像
images. And here is the solution If you want run a virtual machine with
這是解決方案。如果你想運行一個Ubuntu 以外的作業系統
OS other than Ubuntu. For example here we have provides a CentOS 7 image. For creating
的虛擬機。舉例來說，這裡我們使用 CentOS 7 映像。要創建
virtual machine using CentOS 7 it is very easy. "multipass launch" first,
使用 CentOS 7 的虛擬機很容易。“multipass launch”，
Specify which directory the image is at. and --name CentOS 7. Ah, here
首先指向映像在的那個目錄，然後 "--name CentOS 7"。啊，這裡
we can also customize specifications that we need. Very popular and
我們還可以定制我們需要的規格。multipass非常受歡迎和
very good feature of multipass, that is we can also create a virtual machine --cloud-init http.
非常好的特色是，我們還可以創建一個虛擬機 --cloud-init http。
So we don't need to download the image if we install or we create. but
因此，如果我們在安裝或創建時不需要下載映像。
we only need links from existing repositories available. And we can directly launch or
我們只需要來自現有存儲庫的連結。我們可以從可用的映像儲存庫連結
create virtual machine from images from URL which is already available in the repository
直接啟動或創建虛擬機。
directly. So we don't need to download again. But with this method we have to
所以我們不需要重新下載。但是用這種方法，我們必須
make sure that is internet connection. Why? because we download directly from the center or repository
確保網路連接。為什麼？因為我們直接從中心或存儲庫下載
image and install it directly, like that. Next, there is information. In this information we can
映像並直接安裝它，就像這樣。接下來是 "info"。在這些資料中，我們可以
see detailed specifications and what is in the instance. Example here multipass
看到詳細的規格和什麼東西在實例中。例如在這裡，
--info instance-demo. We can see info from virtualization with the demo-instance name that already
"multipass --info instance-demo"。我們可以看到之前創建的名字是"instance-demo"虛擬化
we have made before. In addition, this information we can also customize the format. Example here
的詳細資訊。此外，我們還可以自定義這些資訊的格式。例如在這裡
the format of the virtual machine info is YAML. So we just add the "--format yaml" format.
虛擬機資訊的格式為 YAML。所以我們只需添加“--format yaml”格式。
Then there is the "list" command. "multipass ls" or it stands for the "list" it works for
然後是 “list” 命令。“multipass ls” ，也就是 "list" ，
see all the virtual machines that we have create in multipass. Besides that "ls" is also almost
用來查看我們在Multipass中創建的所有虛擬機。除此之外“ls”也幾乎
same as info. In "ls" we can see info from the virtual machine that we have created
和 "info"一樣。在 “ls” 中，我們能夠以格式的形式看到
in the form of a format. For example, here the format is YAML or JSON. Then there is a menu or command-line start,
我們創建的虛擬機的資料。例如，這裡的格式是 YAML 或 JSON。接下來是 "start"
stop, and delete. If "start" the function is to run a virtual machine. If "stop"
“stop”, “delete”命令行。如果是 “start”，就是運行虛擬機。如果“stop”
its function is to stop the virtual machine. If "delete" is deleting a virtual machine.
它的功能是停止虛擬機。如果 “delete” 就是刪除虛擬機。
Next, here are the features that really good matter, very good for
接下來，這裡是非常重要的功能，非常適合
developers. Here there is a "recover" menu. When we incorrectly "delete" on the virtual machine, then
開發者。這裡有一個 “recover”。當我們在虛擬機上不小心刪除虛擬機時，那麼
state of the virtual machine that we have created before and we have deleted, it is not deleted
我們之前創建並刪除的虛擬機的狀態，並沒有被自動刪除
automatically. The state is simply "deleted". Not permanently deleted. So with state
狀態只是“deleted”，不是永久刪除。所以在 "deleted"的狀態下，
"deleted" we can recover those instances. But if it iss an instance
我們可以恢復那些實例。但如果真的想要自動永久刪除
it really wants to be deleted and automatically permanently, we can use "multipass purge".
實例的話，我們可以使用 "multipass purge”。
Next there are two options to access an instance or multipass virtual machine.
接下來有兩個選項可以訪問實例或multipass虛擬機。
The first uses the shell method. The second using the exec method. If we use
第一種使用shell方法。第二個使用exec方法。如果我們使用
exec method, then we don't need to login anymore to the virtual machine shell that we have created.
exec 方法，那麼我們就不需要登入我們創建的虛擬機的shell。
We just need to run multipass exec, name what is the instance, then requirements or information
我們只需要執行 "multipass exec"、實例的名稱，還有我們想要得到的
what we want to get. Example here "--lsb_release -a | grep ^Codename"
要求或資訊。在這裡的例子，“--lsb_release -a | grep ^Codename”
This means that we want to get information about the codename or OS version that we are using in the virtual machine
這表示我們想要獲取有關我們在虛擬機中使用的代號或作業系統版本的資訊
without logging into the shell. Or without login into the virtual machine. While "shell"
不需要登入shell或虛擬機。另一方面，"shell"
we can use it to shell or we can login to the virtual machine directly.
我們可以用它來shell，也可以直接登入虛擬機。
That's the difference between shell and exec. Then again the best feature is get and set.
這就是 shell 和 exec 之間的區別。接著最好的功能是 "get" 和 ”set”。
If get by default, multipass already autorun. Ah, maybe we
在"get"預設情況下，multipass 已經自動執行。啊，也許我們
haven't explained that multipass actually have a graphical user interface. So not only
還沒有解釋 multipass 其實有一個圖形使用者界面。所以不僅
command line interface. Multipass also provides graphical user interface. How is the graphical user
命令行界面，Multipass 還提供圖形用戶界面。如果我們在本地開發
this interface if we run a multipass in our local development or local environment?
或本地環境中執行Multipass，圖形使用者介面會如何？
For example on a laptop, the graphical user this interface is automatically set to auto-start.
例如在筆記本電腦上，圖形使用者界面會自動設定為自動啟動。
Ah, with this get we can find out how to configure auto-start in multipass.
透過這個"get"，我們可以了解如何在Multipass中配置自動啟動。
Then there is the set command. Its function is the opposite of get. If
然後是 "set"命令。它的功能與get相反。如果是
get it retrieves an information. If set i.e. apply a configuration.
get，它獲取資訊。如果是"set"，則是設定。
Example here set client.gui.autostart=false. value is [false]. It means we set
在這個範例中，設置 client.gui.autostart=false。值為 [false]。這表示我們設置
graphical user interface of multipass [false]. This means that the graphical user interface
Multipass的圖形使用者界面為[false]。當我們設置 [false] 時，
will not run automatically anymore when we set [false]. Next we will discuss
這表示該圖形使用者界面將不再自動運行。接下來我們討論
about the existing networking on multipass. By the default in Linux is that there is only one multipass
關於Multipass的現有網路。Linux 中的預設設置是只有一個 Multipass
interfaces. Then what about when we need two interfaces in a multipass virtual machine?
接口。那麼當我們在Multipass虛擬機中需要兩個接口時呢？
The solution is that we can use the driver addition of LXD where the driver will be
解決的辦法是我們可以在驅動橋接所在的地方
bridged. The first one we install first first LXD. The second we configure LXD with
添加LXD的驅動。第一個命令我們先安裝LXD。第二個命令我們藉由 “lxd init”
command "lxd init". And then we set local driver from multipass to LXD. By default
配置 LXD。然後我們將本地驅動程式設置為 LXD。預設情況下
the same as in other operating systems. For example, in Mac OS, by default we have the correct driver
在其他作業系統也是如此。例如，在 Mac OS 中，預設情況下我們在Multipass的驅動程式
used in multipass is its own multipass. But when we want to use the driver
是它自己的Multipass。但是當我們要使用附加的驅動程式時
additionally then we have to set the multipass to the additional driver. Example here
我們必須將Multipasss設置為附加驅動程式。就像這邊的例子這樣
what's the addition for the driver? Additional drivers LXD, such as that. Ah, after we set additional drivers in LXD.
什麼是附加驅動程式？附加驅動程式 LXD，就像這個。啊，在我們在 LXD 中設置了附加驅動程式之後。
Next we make sure this is using the command that we got earlier. That the local driver is already used in
接下來，我們使用之前的指令，確保在Multipass的本地驅動程序已
multipass using that LXD. Ah, after we make sure the driver we are using LXD,
使用 LXD 。啊，在我們確定我們使用的是LXD的驅動之後，
Then we connect between multipass and the LXD. Ah, the picture explains multipass
我們在Multipass和 LXD 之間進行連接。啊，圖片解釋了multipass
network. here is ens3 ethernet, ethernet devices. Then lxdbr0 Bridge Network Bridge.
網路。這是 ens3 以太網路，以太網路設備。然後是 lxdbr0 Bridge ，網橋。
Then multipass br0. This means that this ens3 is interface of our hypervisor or host
然後mpbr0。這意味著這個 ens3 是我們的虛擬機器監視器(hypervisor)或主機的接口
use. Suppose we use the public hypervisor cloud. Then this is the interface of public
假設我們使用公有hypervisor cloud。那麼這是公有雲的接口
cloud. If we use the local environment like on a laptop. Then ens3 is the assumption
如果我們像在筆記本電腦上一樣使用本地環境。那麼ens3是
interface on our laptop. Next there is lxdbr0. This is an additional interface that
我們筆記本電腦上的預設界面。接下來是 lxdbr0。這是一個我們剛製作的
we just made. By default the name of driver or multipass interface that is mpbr0.
額外的界面。預設情況下，驅動程序或Multipass接口的名稱為 mpbr0。
MP stands for multipass. All network lxd and This mpbr is a bridge from ens3. Ah, how
mp 代表multipass。所有網路 lxd 和這個 mpbr 是來自 ens3 的橋樑。
how to create a virtual machine with network addition? At the end we can declare
如何創建具有附加網路的虛擬機呢？最後我們可以聲明
an option. That is --network adjust to the name of the interface that we have created. Here's the name
一個選項。即 "--network"， 調整為我們創建的接口的名稱。這
the interface is lxdbr0. Ah, when the instance is made then we make sure to use multipass
接口是lxdbr0。當創建實例時，確保有使用
ls, then in the IPv4 section you will see two different IPs already attached to the virtual machine.
"multipass ls"，然後在 IPv4 部分，你會看到兩個不同的 IP 已附加到虛擬機。
The first one at the top is the IP of the driver LXD. The second IP from multipass. Next
頂部的第一個是驅動程序 LXD 的 IP。第二個 IP是Multipass的。接下來
I will explain about the existing integration in multipass. Multipass is very flexible.
我會解釋Multipass中的現有整合。Multipass 非常靈活。
We can integrate the multipass into various like a virtual machine manager. For example
我們可以將 multipass 整合到各種虛擬機管理器中。例如
we can integrate virtual pass into virt-manager or into VirtualBox itself.
我們可以將 virtual pass 整合到 virt-manager 或 VirtualBox 本身。
Therefore, multipass is very suitable for us, who want to create an environment
因此，multipass 非常適合我們這些想要建立環境來開發的人
development. Because with our multipass can run a development on
因為有了我們的 multipass 可以在各種虛擬管理器
various virtual managers. So when we really need a virtual manager
進行開發。所以當我們真的需要一個虛擬管理器時
we can use virt-manager. but the back-end we can use multipass.
我們可以使用 virt-manager。但是後端我們可以使用multipass。
We can also use VirtualBox, but we also use multipass.
我們也可以使用 VirtualBox，但我們也使用 multipass。
In this session I will not demonstrate How is the integration. But here we have
在此會議中，我不會展示如何整合。但在這裡我們有
provide a reference that can be used for multipass integration. Ok, this time I
提供可用於Multipass整合的參考。好的，這次我
will demonstrate How to use multipass and how to create a
將展示如何使用Multipass以及如何創建一個
virtual machine in multipass and how to deploy a web-based application
multipass 中的虛擬機以及如何在Multipass虛擬機中
in a multipass virtual machine. First, make sure you have done a multipass installation.
部署網路應用程式。首先，確保你已安裝Multipass。
Here I use multipass version 1.8.0. To view the version of
這裡我使用Multipass版本 1.8.0。可以在終端機中查看
multipass can be seen in the terminal i.e. using the command "multipass --version".
multipass 版本，也就是使用命令“multipass --version”。
Next to see any image those in multipass can use
接下來查看Multipoass中可以使用的任何映像，
command "multipass find". Ah, by default multipass provides images. The existing images
使用命令“multipoass find”。預設情況下 multipass 提供映像。現有映像
are on ubuntu. Starting from Ubuntu 18.04, Ubuntu 20.04, and 21.04. In addition to the multipass OS image
是 ubuntu 。從 Ubuntu 18.04、Ubuntu 20.04 到 21.04 。除了Multipass作業系統映像
also provides template apps that already exist. There are many options here. Starting from nextcloud,
還提供已經存在的模板應用程式。這裡有很多選擇。從nextcloud，
openhab, plexmediaserver, to minikube. If we want to use kubernetes cluster
openhab、plexmediaserver 到 minikube。如果我們想使用
we can also use minikube for our local development using the Kubernetes cluster.
我們也可以使用 kubernetes 叢集並使用 minikube 進行本地開發。
Then if we want to see virtual existing machines. We can
然後，如果我們想查看現有虛擬機器。我們可以
using the "multipass ls" command. Here are available CentOS 7 Instances or VMs.
使用“multipass ls”命令。這裡有可用的 CentOS 7 實例或虛擬機。
Ah, the difference between image or instance using CentOS 7 with
使用 CentOS 7 的映像或實例和Multipass預設的Ubuntu之間的區別
Ubuntu that already defaults to multipass is in images section. It won't be read in detail here
在於Image欄位。這裡不會詳細顯示資訊
The OS or version or the image used because of the image CentOS 7 is not in the default of multipass.
因為映像 CentOS 7 所使用的作業系統或版本或映像不在預設的 multipass 中。
Then how to create a virtual machine in multipass? To create a virtual machine
那麼如何在multipass中創建虛擬機呢？要創建虛擬機，
run it using the multipass launch command. Then here we can adjust the version
使用 "multipass launch” 命令。然後這裡我們可以調整作業系統版本
OS that we will use. As an example here I am using Ubuntu 20.04 OS.
作為範例，這裡我使用的是 Ubuntu 20.04 作業系統。
Then there is the --name option. --name is like previously explained, namely
然後是 "--name" 選項。"--name" 就像之前解釋的那樣，即
the name of the virtual machine. For example, the name instance-demo. Besides that, we can also
虛擬機的名稱。例如，名稱 instance-demo。除此之外，我們還可以
adjust the CPU we can use for example here the CPU is dual-core. Then the memory is 2GB
調整我們可以使用的 CPU，例如這裡的 CPU 是雙核的。那麼記憶體是2GB
and the disk that will be used is 5GB.
將使用的磁碟為 5GB。
Ah, with this command line we already able to create a multipass.
透過這個命令行，我們已經能夠創建一個Multipass。
This is the process of creating a virtual machine. Ah, as we have seen together, in the terminal
這是創建虛擬機的過程。正如我們一起看到的，在終端機這裡
here is the starting process. It can be said that the steps is very fast starting from creating configuration
是開始的過程。可以說從創建配置開始到啟動一個實例，
and starting an instance. So we don't need another manual to do the installation.
步驟非常快。所以我們不需要另外手動來進行安裝。
We just need to use one command-line, we can already create a virtual machine.
我們只需要使用一個命令行，我們就已經可以創建一個虛擬機了。
Waiting for some instance initiation or the virtual machine. Ah,
等待實例初始化...
here the instance has been created successfully and if... let's see using the command "multipass ls",
這裡實例已成功創建，如果...讓我們看看使用命令“multipass ls”，
here the instance-demo is active.
這裡instance-demo處於活動狀態。
How about when we want to login to virtual the machine we have made? Example here
當我們想要登入到我們製作的虛擬機時呢？這裡以"instance-demo"為例
instance-demo. To log in, you can use "multipass shell" following by its instance name.
要登入，你可以使用“multipass shell”加上實例名稱。
Ah, here we are already logged in shell of the instance-demo virtual machine.
這裡我們已經登入了instance-demo虛擬機的shell。
Make sure we have succeeded ping from within the virtual machine.
確保我們已成功從虛擬機內 ping 。
Ah, now instace has successfully connected to Internet and we can already use virtual
啊，現在實例已經成功連接到網路了，我們已經可以快速且簡易地
machines quickly and easily. Then, how when we want to create a virtual machine
使用虛擬機了。那麼，當我們想要使用 cloud-init 自定義映像
with a custom image using cloud-init? Here I have provided
創建虛擬機時呢？這裡我提供了
viewable cloud-init templates.
可見的 cloud-init 模板。
Ah, here is SSH authorize where are we here can input a public-key
這裡是SSH授權，我們這裡可以輸入SSH公鑰
of SSH which we will use. Then here is the package-update parameter
然後這裡是 package-update 參數
the value is [true]. This means that at the time of installation and making the virtual machine packages are
值為 [true]。這意味著在安裝和製作虛擬機包時
automatically updated. And there is apt-upgrade it is mean if the OS is Ubuntu,
自動更新。並且 apt-upgrade 為true，這表示如果作業系統是 Ubuntu，
This will automatically upgrade the package. and here we can also customize what package
這將自動升級封包。在這裡我們還可以自定義什麼封包
just what we will install. An example here is git, vim, curl, python3, htop, unzip, webserver
是我們將要安裝的。這裡的例子是 git、vim、curl、python3、htop、unzip、webserver、
apache. In fact we can also install directly automatic package docker. there is also an option here
apache。其實我們也可以直接安裝自動打包docker。這裡還有一個選項，
runcmd. Its function is to run a package already installed above.
runcmd。它的功能是運行上面已經安裝的封包。
Then how about the command to make a virtual machine using
那麼使用cloud-init創建虛擬機的命令如何使用？
cloud-init? It's easy. We just need got added --cloud-init option. Then
這很簡單。我們只需要添加 --cloud-init 選項。然後
followed by the name of the cloud-init that we made before. Ah, because
加上我們之前製作的 cloud-init 的名稱。啊，因為
instance-demo has been created, I will add -1 means demo-1.
instance-demo 已創建，我將添加-1 表示demo-1。
Ah, this one has already configured instances. Then the process of starting the instance
這個已經配置好了實例。然後是使用cloud-init啟動實例的過程
using cloud-init. This time it is already in the process of initiating the virtual machine.
這次它已經在啟動虛擬機的過程中了。
The most basic difference because of using cloud-init and we have defined
使用 cloud-init 和不是預設可用的映像的
any package, not the default of the image exists or is available, then the process will follow
自定義的封包，該過程依照
how many packages do we customize or which we defined earlier in cloud-init.
我們自定義了多少個包，或者我們之前在 cloud-init 中定義了哪些包。
The more packages we customize, the more the initiation process will also take longer. And
我們定制的封包越多，啟動過程也就越長。
therefore, make sure the internet connection in creating a multipass in virtual
因此，請確保在Multipass創建虛擬環境時的網路連接穩定
machine in multipass are stable. Ah, currently the instance with cloud-init already
啊，目前已經創建 cloud-init 的實例了
created. Let's see the difference. here are the differences. On configuration or template
讓我們看看區別。以下是差異。在配置或模板上
the previous cloud-init, we define the docker package and here docker is already installed
之前的cloud-init，我們定義了docker包，這裡docker已經安裝好了
and docker has its own IP address. Then on our previous cloud-init configuration
並且 docker 有自己的 IP 地址。然後在我們之前的 cloud-init 配置上
also provides we also import a ssh-key. So to login to the demo-instance-1,
我們還導入了 ssh-key。所以要登入到使用 cloud-init的 demo-instance-1，
which uses cloud-init, there are two options. We can use the key from our SSH,
有兩個選項。我們可以使用 SSH 中的密鑰，
or use shells. For example we use key for the name of the OS corresponds to,
或使用shell。比如我們用key來對應OS的名字，
to login according to the name of the OS. For example, here the OS is Ubuntu to login
根據作業系統的名稱登入。比如這裡要登入的作業系統是Ubuntu，
into Ubuntu. Okay, here We have successful SSH login to demo-instance-1. How
好的，到這裡我們已經成功透過 SSH 登入到 demo-instance-1。
if we want to login to the demo-instance-1 with shells? It also can be done. Currently we have
如果我們想用shell登錄demo-instance-1呢？也可以做到。目前我們已
successfully logged into demo-instance-1. Next let's demonstrate how to install a
成功登入到 demo-instance-1。接下來讓我們演示如何在Multipass虛擬機上
web-based apps on a multipass virtual machine. Make sure the web server is running
安裝一個網路應用程式。先確保網路伺服器正在運行
well. Okay now let's start apache first. Apache is already running.
好。好的，現在讓我們先啟動 apache。Apache 已經在運行。
Make sure we enable it so that it automatically runs when the instance is rebooted or stopped. Then
確保我們啟用它，以便它在實例重啟或停止時自動運行。然後
by default the apache directory is in /var/www/html.
預設情況下，apache 目錄在/var/www/html 中。
Here I will be in /var/www first. And then
在這裡，我將首先進入 /var/www。進而
I will take the web that I already provided by using the wget command.
我將使用 wget 命令獲取我已經提供的網站。
Ah, here is a website available the template I've used for
啊，這裡有一個用過的模板網站
demo at this time. Unzip the website data first. Then move all website data
首先解壓網站網站數據。然後使用“sudo cp /var/www/html”
into /var/www/html using "sudo cp /var/www/html" As it is.
移動所有網站數據到 /var/www/html。
Ok, since we moved some directory too then we need the -R option.
好的，因為我們也移動了一些目錄，所以我們需要 -R 選項。
We make sure in the current directory the data are already enterd with our website data.
我們確保在當前目錄中，數據已經與我們的網站數據一起輸入。
Let's look at the permissions here. It stil owned by "root". We have to adjust the
讓我們看看這裡的權限。它仍然歸“root”所有。我們必須先調整
ownership first. The ownership of the webserver Apache on Ubuntu is www-data:www-data.
所有權。Ubuntu 上的Apache網絡伺服器的所有權是 www-data:www-data。
-R means all files that is in the directory /var/www/html (recursive)
"-R" 表示所有在目錄/ var / www / html（遞迴）的文件
will be authorized to www-data:www-data. Like this
將被授權到 www-data:www-data。像這樣
if we look back at the current owne, it has changed to www-data.
如果我們重新檢視現有的擁有者，它已經變成了 www-data。
Next we make sure in the web browser is accessable with the private IP of the virtual machine.
接下來，我們確保在 Web 瀏覽器中可以使用虛擬機的私有 IP 訪問。
Here the IP is 10.250.1.146. When we access the browser make sure the website is running.
這裡的 IP 是 10.250.1.146。當我們訪問瀏覽器時，請確保網站正在運行。
Ah, now the website is running.
現在網站正在運行。
That's a simple and easy way to run a website on a multipass virtual machine.
這是一個簡單易用的方式，在Multipass虛擬機上運行一個網站。
So with multipass we don't need install an operating system manually anymore.
因此，有了 Multipass，我們就不再需要手動安裝作業系統了。
We no longer need to install services Manually. because of these services
我們不再需要手動安裝服務。因為這些服務
we can adjust it in cloud-init earlier. So as a developer we are of course
我們可以在cloud-init調整。因此，作為開發人員，當然
will be faster in creating or deploying an app using multipass.
使用Multipass創建或部署應用程式會更快速。
That is all from me. I am Nur Hamim. Hope to see you at the next opportunity. Thank you.
這就是全部。我是Nur Hamim。希望下次有機會再見。謝謝。